And now the snakes are on the alert.
This is the best feeding opportunity
they will get all year.
On flat ground, a baby iguana
can outrun a racer snake.
But others are waiting in ambush.
Another hatchling has its first glimpse
of a dangerous world.
A snake's eyes aren't very good.
But they can detect movement.
So, if the hatchling keeps its nerve,
it may just avoid detection.
A near escape.
The lucky survivors could begin learning
the unique way of life demanded
by this hostile island.
As they mature, young males
begin to explore
the boundaries of the pride's territory.
Red has ventured out alone.
And blunders straight into the middle
of the hyena clan.
He's trapped by over 20 of them.
The pack tries to wear him down.
This number of hyenas could kill him.
It's impossible to fight them
all at once.
He can't keep them at bay much longer.
He's tiring fast.
His ally, Tortue, has heard
the commotion.
Now, the odds have changed.
Even for twenty hyenas, a pair of
male lions is too much to take on.
During the dry season,
over half a million terns crowd
onto this remote atoll
in the Indian Ocean.
Their chicks are still
in their dark juvenile plumage.
They vary in age.
Whilst the more advanced chicks
take to the air,
others aren't quite ready yet.
Those just starting to learn to fly
use the shallow lagoon that occupies
the center of the atoll
as their training ground.
It's difficult for some of them
to stay aloft for long.
Giant trevallies.
Usually, they are solitary hunters,
but about 50 of them have come here
from neighboring reefs
attracted by this abundance
of potential prey.
The fledglings stay out of the water
if they can.
They even drink on the wing.
If the trevally are to catch one now,
they have to up their game.
So, there is a fish here that amazingly
has a brain capable of calculating
the air speed, altitude, and trajectory
of a bird.
The time comes when every fledgling
has to take to the air
and collect food for itself.
Their parents lead them
to the training grounds.
If they are to survive,
they must learn quickly.
After a month of practicing
over the lagoon,
the youngsters start to leave
and take their chances out
over the open sea.
Exhausted from his swim,
the bear must regain his strength.
The next day, a sea fog
shrouds the island.
The walruses sense that
they're in danger.
Using the fog as cover,
the bear approaches the herd.
The adults close ranks
around their young,
presenting a wall of blubber
and hide.
He tests the barrier,
but it stands firm.
It appears that the world's largest
land carnivore has met his match.
There must be a chink
in the armor somewhere.
Not here.
This female walrus is shielding her pup.
If he can just prize her off,
the bear's paws and teeth
can't penetrate her thick hide.
With the herd retreating to water,
the bear must move quickly.
Having failed with one,
he heads straight for another.
The chance of his first meal in months
is slipping away.
He seems increasingly desperate.
It's now or never.
He must avoid the stabbing tusks
if he's to win.
The flailing walrus
is immensely powerful
and drags the bear away
from the shallows
towards the safety of the herd.
It slips from his grasp.
Mantids will eat anything that moves,
including other mantids.
Time to leave.
This tiny insect is now
open to attack
from predators lurking
in the undergrowth.
Whether an individual mantis survives
or not is partly a matter of chance.
Whether it's spotted by a predator.
Whether it turns right or left.
So far, its luck has held.
But this hungry jumping spider
is still in pursuit.
A mantis is born with
exceptional eyesight.
But the spider's is even better.
Although this young mantis
can't yet fly,
its long forelegs evolved
to catch prey give it reach.
There seems to be no escape.
But this mantis has a surprising line
in self-defense.
Kung fu, praying mantis style.
Of course, it's all bluff.
Trying to look bigger
and confuse its enemy.
But it's got away with it.
Just staying alive
for its first few hours
is a significant accomplishment
for a newly hatched insect.
But there's still a long way to go.
With a bit of luck,
in 2 months' time,
it will be as big and beautiful
as this orchid mantid.
Or maybe not.
After all, mantids are cannibals.
Stony canyons provide a sanctuary
for animals throughout the Middle East.
Like Nubian ibex.
These wild goats can only survive here
because precious water bubbles
to the surface in springs.
In summer, the females come to drink
at these pools every day.
The pool is guarded by a male ibex.
He has exclusive access to the females
who come here.
He tastes the air to see
if any of them are ready to mate.
But this is such a prized spot
that inevitably he has competition.
Getting the upper ground will be key.
The males' skulls are specially
reinforced to take a battering.
They're evenly matched.
The battle could last up to an hour.
But when a third male joins in,
no one seems to know who to fight.
The party is soon broken up
by a telltale smell in the air.
The ibex are right to be skittish.
Bedouin have always been
skilled hunters.
Kenya, famous for its big cats,
the supreme hunters.
Cheetahs specialize in hunting at speed.
Though fast, they're fragile creatures
built to sprint after small prey.
They don't have the strength or weight
of a lion to bring down larger animals.
This male is different.
He doesn't hunt alone.
He's learned that there is strength
in numbers.
But here, there are not just two,
but three cheetahs.
A band of brothers.
They have changed their tactics
and by doing so
have taken their prey
by surprise.
They have learned that working together
they can bring down large prey.
An ostrich, a bird that towers over a
cheetah and is more than twice as heavy.
It can't fly to escape danger,
but it can lash out with a deadly kick.
A female unaware as yet of any danger.
Even with three of them,
this is still highly risky.
If one gets injured, the other two
couldn't hope to tackle such large prey.
On the other hand, if they get it right,
the rewards are huge.
The male has spotted
one of the brothers, but only one.
It's not too worried.
Then suddenly, there are three.
The female is slower to realize the
danger, and the cheetahs switch targets.
It takes the combined effort
and weight of all three
brothers to bring down
this powerful bird.
Even now, the ostrich
could land a fatal kick.
So far, the brothers are winning.
Ostriches have yet to find a way
to foil such tactics.
High up in the Rockies,
one of the greatest
gatherings in the wild west
is underway.
For most of the year, bison bulls
and cows live separate lives.
But for a few weeks
in late summer,
thousands congregate
in this Yellowstone Valley.
It's the rut, the mating season,
and the biggest bulls are busy
guarding their harems.
A dominant bull might mate
with over 50 females.
For the calves born this year, now
is the time to stretch their young legs.
But as the herd grows,
so tensions rise.
The rut takes a heavy toll
on the big bulls.
So, arriving now could give
this young contender an edge.
But, there's life in the old bull yet.
Head to head, the challenger
more than holds his own.
Then, he makes a small mistake.
Shunted aside, his challenge
is brutally ended.
The young bull gambled everything
and has paid a heavy price.
Somehow, in this melee
of 60,000 or so penguins,
a parent has to find its chick.
It returns to the place
where it last left its chick
in the hope that it might
still be close by.
But, chicks tend to wander.
So, the adult has to call to it.
The chick responds,
and they slowly home in on one another.
The plaintive entreaties of the chick
stimulates the adult to regurgitate
a mouthful of fish.
With the return of one parent,
the other is free
to go to sea to feed for itself.
Aware of the leopard seal's presence,
the penguins press together
at the ice edge,
unwilling to be the first
to risk diving in.
Occasionally, the seal comes out
onto the ice and attempts to grab one.
But, its most successful strategy by far
is to lie in wait.
It hides behind the corner of ice.
The emperors gain confidence
and make a dash for it.
The first wave of penguins escape.
Once in open water, they'll be safe.
But, the seal is alerted
by the noise
and through the mass of bubbles,
it makes its attack.
Almost invariably, it makes a kill.
Encouraged by the absence
of the seal,
the remaining penguins make a break
for the open sea.
In time, their chicks will fledge.
And when the Antarctic autumn
is near its end,
these adults will walk across
the newly formed ice
to endure yet another winter
on the frozen sea.
♪ ♪